Guide to the Records of the Office of Research Services/Office of Sponsored Programs RG.9.4
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of Research Services/Office of Sponsored Programs
1940-2005
1949-1997
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of Research Services
New York University. Office of Sponsored Programs
RG.9.4
11.50 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
These Research Administration Papers incorporate materials generated during the years 1940-2005, including selected and duplicated material created 1940-1946 in the Office of Chancellor Harry Woodburn Chase, within other university units, and within the Office of Research Services 1952-1971, and its renamed successor Office of Sponsored Programs 1971-2005. The Papers have been divided into six series.
Conditions Governing Access note
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Arrangement note
The collection has been organized topically into six series:
List:ordered
Administration
University Administration
Research Administration
Research Administration, Related Units
Schools/Units
Sponsor Matters
Historical Note
With the passage in 1862 by the U.S. Congress of the Morrill Act an its subsequent approval, in 1887, of the Hatch Act, federal funds began to flow to higher education in this country, first to states for the establishment of land-grant colleges of agriculture and of the mechanic arts (1), and then to those newly established schools for the institution of agricultural experiment stations and the conduct of agricultural research (2).
From those distant beginnings evolved the role of universities as the primary home for basic research in the United States and the training ground for succeeding generations of scientists. An important stimulus in this process arose in the international sector, in pre-World War II days. Rearmament was under way in Germany. Planners and designers were drawing upon weapons technology advances from World War I, adapting them for strategic purposes and incorporating them into new military equipment and material.
In this country, groups of scientists concerned with German remilitarization, many viewing it as preparatory to a second world war began communicating to the highest levels of the U.S. government their awareness of these events. One outcome was the establishment of a White House-based Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD), its purpose to collaborate with military scientists and, with the realization that "the greatest practicable source of otherwise untapped scientific expertise lay in colleges and universities," (3) to identify and contract with campus-based scientists capable of meeting defense related technical needs as well as preparing cadres of scientifically and technically competent manpower.
A consequence of this new relationship was the realization that while numerous U.S. faculties included academics with the desired of adaptable skills and knowledge, often their institutions' business operations were not structured to handle the particular administrative demands in play. It has been said that "one of the most significant contributions of OSRD was the writing and administration of a form of contract which reconciled the requirements" of accountability for the use of federal funds with the need of scientists for freedom to address the problems before them. (4) However, on the business side of many involved universities new assignments and often a considerable degree of improvisation were called for in order both to provide research faculty with the requisite support services contract fulfillment called for and address previously unfamiliar matters such as the identification of associated direct and indirect costs of these projects, space allocations, and secrecy issues.
Moving into the post-war years, university reputations became increasingly tied to levels of funded research as those universities identified as research universities gained prominence. A specialized bureaucracy in the universities and in federal agencies developed to manage these programs, which over time became increasingly complex, both in the nature of much research and in the demands of its administration and management. On campuses, the administrative function(s) supporting the programs of research became known as research administration; such offices often reported to the financial side of the house. Some others evolved with an academic orientation and reported to an academic officer.
Scientists active in the programs OSRD put together during the war years often later became advocates for continuing federal funding of campus-based research, positing the notion of a special partnership. At the federal level the National Science Foundation was created in 1950 to provide academic scientists with funding for investigator-initiated research. That era also saw the emergence of funders such as the Office of Naval Research, Air Force Office of Sponsored Research, Army Research Office, etc., agencies spun off from defense mission sponsors with a new orientation to academic initiated research ideas. (5)
Events in the 1960s and 1970s brought changes in this atmosphere. "Qualitative aspects of higher education were being more closely examined by politicians, by the citizenry, and by educators themselves." (6) U.S. involvement in Vietnam, the ensuing student anti-war demonstrations and campus uprisings, along with emotions and political residue from the Cold War had given rise to widespread anti-academic sentiment. The collaborative university-government relationship increasingly came under attack in Congress, the White House, and by some interest groups. Expensive, mission-driven research not feasible on campuses gained support. The government-university relationship as a vehicle for implementation of social change (consent for the use of human subject, oversight of the use of animals in experimentation, maintenance of a drug-free work environment, property alteration to facilitate hiring of disabled workers, etc.) became significant.
The nature of the relationship often became more adversarial than collegial. One perhaps unintended consequence of the foregoing new initiatives was that they required the employment of campus-based compliance officers at almost the same time as federal Office of Management and Budget imposed new limitations on university expenditures associated with research. Tellingly lobbying for funding, including "earmarks," a political process, often substituted for prior selection processes usually based on technical competitiveness.
Much related to these matters is reflected in this modest collection. Again in consultation with the University Archivist it was deemed unnecessary to provide detailed guidance by series to users of this collection. A few topics have been highlighted below. The Box and Folder List, following, is designed to guide interested researchers to particular matters reflected within the collection.
New York University (NYU) was not a first tier institution at the time of the outset of this collection. It was, nevertheless, a significant player in the new environment of 1940-1946, providing contracted-for research and training services to the military, especially at the then College of Engineering at the University Heights campus, research at the University Medical Center, and the work of the Mathematics Institute emerging at Washington Square under the direction of Dr. Richard Courant. The excerpts from the Chase Papers mentioned above are incorporated into this collection as the first entry in Series III, Research Administration and titled here "The World War II Era." They reflect some of those early, and sometimes temporary, institutional assignments. A few years later, postwar faculty interested in advancing their programs of research and seeking new institutional administrative and financial support to facilitate their work can be seen in the 1949 report by a committee of Graduate Arts and Science faculty which follows the Chase section. Notably, in that same year NYU was invited to Association of American Universities (AAU) membership, the national association of premier research universities in North America. Also in Series III, new appointments and offices emerge, charged with generally stated responsibility for various management and administrative activity deemed pertinent to the increasing availability of external funding for research and growing faculty interest in obtaining it. For a sense of the functional interconnectedness among offices reporting to various officers/deans at he time of this collection, see Series III, Series IV, Research Administration, Other Units, and Series V, Schools/Units.
NYU undertook an ambitious development plan in 1964 under the leadership of President James M. Hester (1962-1975), (R.G. 3.0.7). Records pertinent to the research administration function, covering developments related to the university's proposal to the National Science Foundation's Science Development Program, funded at NYU 1969, are found in both the Hester collection and, more completely, including the university's management of the multi-million dollar grant, in the Papers Chancellor/Executive Vice President Sidney Borowitz (1972-1977) (R.G. 6.0.7), some of the latter of which as described above were transferred from Office of Sponsored Programs records into that collection at the time of the Borowitz Papers' processing.
Intellectual property considerations arose in connection with some projected university-industry research relationships; in some instances like concerns were also generated by contractual terms and conditions proposed by publically funded sponsors. Among them were matters of freedom to publish, patent and copyright ownership, and rights in data. Institutional responses of ten took the route of empanelment of faculty or joint recommending policy to the university administration. Detail about these matters can be found in Series I, Administration, and Series VI, Sponsor Matters. Series I and Series II, University Administration, include documentation of the process of institutional consideration and response to government compliance initiatives of the period. Representatives of school research administration offices also participated in these discussion and development activities. See Compliance and Policy committee membership lists, etc., Series I.
At no time during the period of this collection did NYU centralize the research administration function. While from 1952 onward the office initially named Office of Research Services, which reported to the Chancellor, served as "Authorizing Official" for the submission of proposals from most university units to external funding sources-a form of signature authority which committed the institution to the proposal and specified acceptance of its obligation to accept funding awarded and manage it under terms previously agreed to or to be negotiated in advance of acceptance of any such funding-Medicine and the Mathematics Institute (renamed the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences in 1958 in Dr. Courant's honor) retained that authority for those units as did Engineering until its transfer to Brooklyn's Polytechnic University in 1972.
At this writing in 2008, there has been some movement toward centralization of authority. Electronic transmission of proposals has become a reality, and unitis with local research administration offices, including the previously independent Courant Institute, submit proposals directly once cleared by the central office. The Medical Center operation, however, remains completely independent.
Sources:
(1) Axt, Richard G. The Federal Government and Financing Higher Education. New York: Columbia University Press, 1952.
(2)True, Alfred Charles. A History of Agricultural Experimentation and Research in the U.S. U.S. Department of Agriculture: Miscellaneous Publication No. 251, 1937.
(3)Stewart, Irvin. Organizing Scientific Research for War—An Administrative History of the Office of Scientific Research and Development. Boston: Little Brown and Company, 1948.
(4)Ibid.
(5)Dupree, A. Hunter. Science in the Federal Government. Cambridge: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1957.
(6)Wilson, John T. Academic Science Higher Education and the Federal Government 1950-1983. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1983.
Provenance
This collection was transferred to the University Archives in two accessions. In 1997 the Office of Sponsored Programs transferred the contents of two Paige boxes. The bulk of the collection was then transferred to the archives in early in 2008.
Related Archival Materials note
The contents of one of the Paige boxes deposited by the Office of Sponsored Programs in the University Archives in 1997 was entered in to the collection of the Papers of Sidney Borowitz, Chancellor/Executive Vice President of the University 1972-1977 (RG 6.0.7)in 2003. This addition expanded the Borowitz collection's materials covering the University Science Development Program.
Scope and Content Note
These papers reflect the origins and evolution of New York University's research administration function, formed variously at the university in the Office of the Chancellor, the Finance Office, the Office of Research Services, successor Office of Sponsored Programs and in some schools. Included among them is a set of duplicated copies of letters and memoranda from the Papers of Chancellor Harry Woodburn Chase (RG 3.0.5), found in Series III and identified here as "The World War II Era," 1940-1946.
This collection was transferred to the University Archives in two accessions. The bulk of it, consisting of nine transfiles, was transferred early in 2008 from the Office of Sponsored Programs (OSP). Additionally, the contents of two Paige boxes, transferred from OSP to the Archives in 1997, were entered into this collection, namely Annual Reports 1972-1975, 1978-1979, 1981-1988, 1989-2004, and Monthly reports of Award Received at the University, 1953-1988; successive editions of the "Sponsored Research and Training Programs Manual," 1956-1997; and materials documenting aspects of the early development of what is today the Faculty of Arts and Science Neural Science Department. Finally, the contents of a third Paige box deposited by OSP in the University Archives in 1997 were entered into he collection of the Papers of Sidney Borowitz, chancellor/Executive Vice President of the University 1972-1977, (RG 6.0.7) when it was processed in 2003, expanding the collection's materials covering the University Science Development Program first funded at the University by the National Science Foundation in 1969.
The collection is composed essentially of correspondence, memoranda, documentation of the inception of university policies associated with its relationships with federal, state and local funding agencies, along with copies of sponsor grant and contract terms and (ORS/OSP) staffing plans and proposals.
In consultation with the University Archivist, and in recognition that by virtue of the charge of this Office, it functioned of necessity in on-going working association with a variety of other university units, the collection has been structured, perhaps arbitrarily, in an effort to permit an appreciation of that scope and institutional interconnectedness. The papers have thus been grouped into six series: Administration; University Administration; Research Administration; Research Administration, Related Units; Schools/Units; and Sponsor Matters.
Folders and in some instances individual documents were shifted in the interest of consistency and clarity. Some content overlap exists; an occasional Separation Sheet calls attention to several of significance. The collection is in good physical condition. Aging tissue copies and some extant duplicated materials were photocopied and/or recopied, and originals discarded, as were duplicates when found. Material is for the most part organized chronologically in folders. Folder titles generally reflect date and broad content subject matter.
Project manuals.; Correspondence.; Grants.; Contracts; Memorandums.; Annual reports.; Borowitz, Sidney, 1918-; New York University. Office of the Chancellor; New York University. Finance Office; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; New York University. College of Dentistry; New York University. College of Medicine; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955; United States. Department of the Army; United States. Navy; United States. Department of the Air Force; Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences; New York University. Office of Academic Affairs; New York University. School of Education; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Science
- Administration, 1987-1996
  - Compliance Committees, Task force on Animal Programs Management, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Compliance Committees, Task force on Animal Programs Management, Animal Oversight, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Animal Oversight, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Related Matters, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Realted Matters, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Drug Free Schools and Campuses, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Compliance Committees, Task Force on Animal Programs Management, Environmental Services, Safety, 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Compliance Committees, Integrity in Research, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Compliance Committees, Misconduct in Science, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Compliance Committees, Misconduct in Science, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Compliance Committees, Radiation Safety, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Policy Committees, Research Advisory Council, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Committee, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Committee, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Committee, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Group, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Policy Committees, Sponsored Research Working Groups, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Intellectual Property, AAU Survey and Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Intellectual Property, AAU Surveys and Reports, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Intellectual Property, Clinical Trials, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Intellectual Property, COGR Issues, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Intellectual Property, Confidentiality Issues, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Intellectual Property, Confidentiality Issues, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Intellectual Property, Confidentiality Issues, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Intellectual Property, Confidentiality Issues, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Intellectual Property, Confidentiality Issues, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Intellectual Property, Copyright, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Intellectual Property, Copyright, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Intellectual Property, Copyright, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Intellectual Property, NIH Commercialization Inquiry, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Intellectual Property, Univ-Industry Relations, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Intellectual Property, Univ-Industry Relations, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Intellectual Property, Univ-Industry Relations, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Intellectual Property, University Patents, Inc, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Intellectual Property, University Patents, Inc, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Intellectual Property, University Patents, Inc, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Intellectual Property, Science and Engineering Technology, Inc (Successor to University Patents, Inc), 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Intellectual Property, Office of Industrial Liason, 1989-1995 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- University Administration
  - Academic Affairs, Office of, Assistant Vice President, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Assistant Provost, Office of, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Assistant Provost/Vice Provost, Office of, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Vice Chancellor, Office of, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Vice Chancellor, Office of, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vice Chancellor, Office of, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Vice Chancellor, Office of, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Vice Chancellor/ Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Deputy Chancellor, Office of, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Research Administration
  - The World War II Era, 1940-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Organized Research, 1949-1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research Services, Office of, 1952-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Research Services, Office of, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Research Services/Sponsored Programs, Office of (name change 1971), 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sponsored Programs, Office of, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sponsored Programs, Office of, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)